George Brandon Saul Papers
George Brandon Saul Papers
1912-1969
Saul, George Brandon, 1901-
10.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American educator, author, poet, composer.
Correspondence (1930-1969); manuscripts of books, musical scores, poems, and plays; printed materials including articles, book reviews, books, clippings, and short stories; school notebooks; and photographs.
Correspondents include Morse Allen, Padraic Colum, T.R. Henn, Desmond Maxwell, Alex Preminger, and Charles W. Stork.
149564
Biographical History
George Brandon Saul, Ph.D., is an American educator, author and composer of music. He was born in Shoemakersville, Pennsylvania, Nov 1, 1901, the son of Daniel Brandon and Mary E. Stamm Saul, and attended the University of Pennsylvania, receiving his B.A. in 1921, M.A. in 1930, and Ph.D. in 1932. A member of the English faculty of the University of Connecticut since 1924, Mr. Saul has been a full professor there since 1942. Since 1956 Dr. Saul has served as a technical writing consultant for Pratt & Whitney Aircraft. Dr. Saul resides at 4 Gilbert Road, Storrs, Connecticut. He spent a sabbatical year (1966-1967) in Ireland doing research on modern Irish literature.
Mr. Saul is the author of plays, short stories, articles and book reviews, and the composer of musical compositions and songs. His poems have appeared in numerous periodicals and anthologies. His pubiished works include The Cup of Sand, 1923; Bronze Woman, 1930; Unimagined Rose, 1937; Only Necessity, 1941; Selected Lyrics, 1947; October Sheaf, 1951; Major Types of English Literature, 1935; Hound and Unicorn, 1966; A.E. Coppard: His Life and His Poetry, 1932; The Elusive Stallion, 1947; Handbook of English Grammar and Writing Conventions, 1953; Stephens, Yeats and Other Irish Concerns, 1954; The Shadow of the Three Queens, 1953; Prolegomena to the Study of Yeat's Poems, 1957; Prolegomena to the Study of Yeats's Plays, 1958; Carved in Finduine, 1966; and The Wild Queen, 1967.
A member of the Poetry Society of America and the Modern Language Association, Mr. Saul lives in Storrs, Connecticut. He married his first wife, Dorothy M. Ayers, in 1925 and with her had one son, George Brandon II. After Dorothy's death 1937, Brandon married Eileen S. Lewis, with whom he had two children, Michael Brandon and Barbara Brigid.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The George Brandon Saul Papers consists of the original accession and two sets of additions which have not been integrated and are listed separately in the inventory below.
1966-1967 accessions
The main accession consists of correspondence, subject files, manuscripts, and published material. Correspondence is arranged alphabetically by author (incoming) or chronoligically (outgoing). The Subject file, which is arranged alphabetically, consists of Dr. Saul's college course work and notes, photographs of himself and his faamily, and other related items. Dr. Saul's Manuscripts, arranged alphabetically by title, include articles, books, book reviews, essays, letters to editors, musical scores, plays, poems, short stories, and theses. Published material includes articles, books, book reviews, letters to editors, newspaper clippings, poems, programs, short stories, and theses. Additional material received in late 1966 and early 1967 has been integrated into the main collection and filed in the appropriate box/folder.
1968 additions
The 1968 additions to the George Brandon Saul Papers cover the years 1918, 1930-1931, and 1964-1968, and consist of two series. Correspondence, 1930-1931, 1964-1968, includes letters from friends, associates and publishers concerning the writing and publishing of works, the establishment of an Irish literature program in an American university and a sabbatical leave research trip to Ireland. Important correspondents include Homer Babbidge, 1964-1968; Padraic Colum, 1966; Ruth Hall, 1930-1931; Tony Knowland, 1966-1967; E'oin McKiernan, 1966-1968; and Mrs. Frank (Harriet) O'Connor, 1968. The letters are arranged chronologically, and there is an index to important correspondents on 3x5 slips in Box 1. Manuscript and published material, 1918, 1930, 1965-1968, includes a bibliogrpahy, book reviews, books, a monograph, musical compositions, a novella, and poems by Mr. Saul. Also included is a review of Mr. Saul's book, The Wild Queen. These writings are arranged alphabetically by type and alphabetically by title within each type.
1969 additions
The 1969 additions to the George Brandon Saul Papers cover the years 1920, 1935, 1937, and 1964-1969 and include correspondence, memorabilia, and writings. Correspondence, 1968-1969, including incoming and outgoing letters, is arranged chronologically. Memorabilia, 1920, consists of three high school notebooks, two for Latin and one for forestry. The bulk of the 1969 additions are Saul's Writings (1935, 1937, and 1964-1969). They are divided into six groups: book reviews, books, musical scores, a play, poems, and a radio broadcast. The book reviews are arranged alphabetically by the title of the book reviewed. Drafts and published copies of books, including books of folk tales and books of poetry, are arranged alphabetically by book title. The musical scores consist of three short pieces and, like the short poems, are arranged alphabetically. There is only one play and one radio broadcast script. Arrangement is alphabetical within each group; book reviews are arranged by the title of the book being reviewed.
Other additions
The collection also has one box containing multiple accessions from 1971, 1976 and 1979, which consists mostly of correspondence and printed material. This unprocessed material is not included in the inventory below and is available only by special permission.
Arrangement of the Collection
See Scope and content above. Note that since the three sets of material have not been integrated, box numbers are not unique. When requesting boxes, please specify the year in addition to the box number to ensure retrieval of the correct items.
Subject and Genre Headings
Music; Literature -- American Poetry; Literature -- American Fiction; Allen, Morse S. (Morse Shepard), 1891-1967.; Colum, Padraic, 1881-1972.; Henn, T. R. (Thomas Rice), 1901-1974.; Maxwell, D. E. S. (Desmond Ernest Stewart), 1925-; Preminger, Alex.; Saul, George Brandon, 1901-; Stork, Charles Wharton, 1881-; American literature -- 20th century.; American literature -- Book reviews.; American poetry -- 20th century.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Books -- Reviews.; Composers -- United States.; Dramatists, American -- 20th century.; Educators -- United States.; Irish-American literature -- 20th century.; Irish Americans.; Music -- 20th century.; Music -- Poetry.; Musicians -- United States.; Novelists, American -- 20th century.; Plays-in-progress.; Poets, American -- 20th century.; Short stories, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts for publication.; Musical scores.; Notebooks.; Poems.; Photographs.; Reviews (documents); Textbooks.; Authors.; Composers.; Dramatists.; Educators.; Musicians.; Novelists.; Poets.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Dr. George B. Saul, 1966-1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence (1966-1967 accessions)
  See also Correspondence (1968 additions) and Correspondence (1969 additions)
  - Incoming
    - A (Box 1)
    - Allen, Morse (Box 1)
    - Alspock, Russell (Box 1)
    - B (Box 1)
    - Brownmiller, Arlan J. (Box 1)
    - C (Box 1)
    - Colum, Padraic (Box 1)
    - Cooper, John W. (Box 1)
    - D-G (Box 1)
    - H (Box 1)
    - Hall, Hazel (Box 1)
    - Henn, T.R. (Box 1)
    - Houseman, Lawrence (Box 1)
    - I-K (Box 1)
    - L (Box 1)
    - Loftur, Richard (Box 1)
    - M (Box 1)
    - Maxwell, Desmond (Box 1)
    - Nicholl, Louise T. (Box 1)
    - Norwood, Robert (Box 1)
    - O-P (Box 1)
    - P.F. Collier & Son (Box 1)
    - Preminger, Alex (Box 1)
    - Q-R (Box 1)
    - Russell, H.L. (Box 1)
    - S (Box 1)
    - Saul (Box 1)
    - Stork, Charles W. (Box 1)
    - T-V (Box 1)
    - Wade Adam (Box 1)
    - Witt, Marion (Box 1)
  - Outoing
    - 1940, 1950-1952, 1956-1958, 1961-1965 (Box 2)
- Subject files (1966-1967 accessions)
  - Anonymous Drawing (Box 2)
  - Courses Taken at University of Pa. Graduate School (Box 2)
  - Course Work & Notes
    - American Literature (Contemporary), 1943 (Box 2)
    - Anglo-Latin Literature (Box 2)
    - Chaucer & Middle English Philology, 1921-1922 (Box 2)
    - Classical Element & Italian Influence in English Literature, 1926 (Box 2)
    - Elizabethan Literature, 1920-1922 (Box 2)
    - English Essayists, 1921-1922 (Box 3)
    - English Metrics and Poetic Theory, 1930-1931 (Box 3)
    - Fine Arts, 1922 (Box 3)
    - Graduate Studies, 1926-1931 (Box 3)
    - Greek (Box 3)
    - History of Literature (American & British), undated (Box 3)
    - Irish Rennaissance & Contemporary English Poetry, 1921 (Box 3)
    - Latin, 1922 (Box 3)
    - Literary Forms, undated (Box 3)
    - Medieval Literature, 1926 (Box 4)
    - Medieval Literature, 1937 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous English, 1923 (Box 4)
    - 19th Century Poetry, 1921; 1922,; 1926,; 1928,; 1930 (Box 4)
    - 19th Century Prose, 1927-1928 (Box 4)
    - The Novel, 18th, 19th, & 20th Centuries, 1921-1923; 1927,; 1928,; 1930,; 1933 (Box 4)
    - Philosophy, 1920-1921 (Box 4)
    - Restoration to French Revolution, 1921; 1929 (Box 4)
    - Roman History, 1922-1923 (Box 5)
    - 17th Century Lyric, undated (Box 5)
  - Description of Traffic Accident with Sketch, 1952 (Box 5)
  - Membership Certificate (Box 5)
  - Photos (Box 5)
  - Undergraduate College Reports & Data (Box 5)
- Manuscripts (1966-1967 accessions)
  See also Manuscripts and published works (1968 additions) and Writings (1969 additions)
  - Articles
    - "A Frenzy of Concentration: Yeat's Verse from 'Responsibilities' to 'The King of the Great Clock Tower' " (Box 5)
    - "Icy Song: The Verse of Elinor Wylie" (Box 5)
    - "Irish Literature" (Box 5)
    - "The Irish Rennaissance" (Box 5)
    - "Minor Irish Miscellany" (Box 5)
    - "Of One Forgotten", June 1951 (Box 5)
    - "Of Tales Half-Forgotten" (Box 5)
    - "The Short Stories of George Moore" (Box 5)
    - "Silver Daughter of the Puritans: Winifred Waller of Norwich Town" (Box 5)
    - "Strange Gods and Far Places: The Short Stories of Lord Dunsany" (Box 5)
    - "A Wild Sowing: The Short Stories of Liam O'Flaherty" (Box 5)
    - "Yeat's Verse Before 'Responsibilities' ", 1960 (Box 5)
  - Books
    - Advice to the Emotionally Perturbed (Married - Past or Present, Willing, or Doubtful) (Box 5)
    - The Age of Yeats: Irish Literature, table of contents, notes & final alterations (Box 5)
    - Blood Shadow (Box 6)
    - Candlelight Rhymes for Early-To-Beds, carbon (Box 6)
    - Carved in Findruine (Box 6)
    - English in Rhyme for Very Young Folk (Box 6)
    - Fundamental Processes of Elementary Algebra: A Concise Review and Reference Summary (Box 6)
    - In the Shadow of Mountains, original and typescript (Box 6)
    - In Luminous Wind (Box 6)
    - A Little Book of Strange Tales (Box 6)
    - A Practical Summary of English Grammar & Associable Conventions, with Exercises, 2 copies (Box 7)
    - Prolegomena to the Study of Yeats' Plays, with notes (Box 7)
    - Prolegomena to the Study of Yeats' Poems, with notes; 2 copies (Box 7)
    - Quintet (Box 7)
    - The Wedding of Sir Gawain and Dame Raynell, translation, with notes and galleys (Box 7)
    - The Wild Queen, with notes; 2 copies (Box 7)
    - The Winged Image and Other Essays in the Yeatsian Era (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews about George Brandon Saul
    - Bronze Woman, 1930 (Box 7)
  - Book Reviews by George Brandon Saul
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Essays
    - "The Brief Fiction of Sean O'Faolain" (Box 8)
    - "Early Irish Poetry" (Box 8)
    - "Essays and Verse", 1936 (Box 8)
    - "The Irish Renaissance" (Box 8)
    - "Later Irish Poetry: Vernacular & English" (Box 8)
    - "Summary Notes on Yeats' Dramatic Dicta and Accomplishment" (Box 8)
    - "Tumult in Lainster", original (Box 8)
    - "Withdrawn in Gold" (Box 8)
  - Letters to Editors
    - Miscellaneous (Box 8)
  - Music
    - "Ad Dei Gloriam", 1965 (Box 9)
    - "At the Cave of Forty Thieves" (Box 9)
    - "The Ballad of Samson" (Box 9)
    - "Butterflies' Night Piece" (Box 9)
    - "Etude in D Major" (Box 9)
    - "Four Songs" and "He Gave His Beloved Certain Rhymes" (Box 9)
    - "Gnomes' March" (Box 9)
    - "Grotesque for Goblins" (Box 9)
    - "Heard Under Cattails" and "The Brewer's Man" (Box 9)
    - "Lyrical Brevities for Piano" (Box 9)
    - "No.1 of Five Carols for Christmastide" (Box 9)
    - "Perhaps on Such a Night" (Box 9)
    - "Ring Out Wild Bells" and "The Watchers" (Box 9)
    - "Rumination, 2nd Theme", 1965 (Box 9)
    - "Sonata Toward Winter", 1941 (Box 9)
    - "Songs for Tenor Voice", 1965 (Box 9)
    - "Two Lovers by the Styx" (Box 9)
    - "Valse" (Box 9)
    - "When on the Marge of Evening" (Box 9)
    - "The Wild Ride" (Box 9)
    - Short pieces (Box 9)
  - Music (photocopies)
    - "Perhaps on Such a Night" (Box 9)
    - "Rumination" (Box 9)
    - "Ring Out Wild Bells", 1965 (Box 9)
    - "Songs for Tenor Voice", 1965 (Box 9)
    - "Two Lovers by the Styx" (Box 9)
    - "When on the Marge of Evening" (Box 9)
    - "The Wild Ride" and "No. 1 of Five Carols for Christmastide" (Box 9)
  - Plays
    - "The Fair Eselt", with notes (Box 10)
    - "Play and Poem", 1922 (Box 10)
    - "The Shine on the Waters", 2 copies (Box 10)
    - "The Trial by Fable" (Box 10)
  - Poems
    - Description of Early Works (Box 10)
    - "Ada and Other Poems", 1919; 2 copies (Box 10)
    - "All Hallows' Eve" (Box 10)
    - "Ballade" (Box 10)
    - "Book I, Poems (Short)", 1916-1919 (Box 10)
    - "Book II, (Short) Poems by G.B. Saul", 1917 (Box 10)
    - "Book IV, Poems", 1917 (Box 10)
    - "Book VI, An Echo from the Sea Caves", 1917 (Box 10)
    - "Book VII, Siren Tide and Other Poems", 1917 (Box 10)
    - "Book IX, Additional Poems", 1918 (Box 10)
    - "Book X, Poems", 1919 (Box 10)
    - "(Book XI, Poems)", 1919 (Box 10)
    - (Book, Miscellaneous), 1928-1933; 1934-1936 (Box 10)
    - "Curse for a Certain Landlady" (Box 10)
    - "Demure Felice" (Box 10)
    - "Epitaph" (Box 10)
    - "Fair Warning" (Box 10)
    - "Felim's Daughter", original, 2 copies (Box 10, 11)
    - "The Foot Withdrawn" (Box 11)
    - "Forest Dawn and Other Verses" (Box 11)
    - "The Ghosts" (Box 11)
    - "Houses of Sorrow", 1920 (Box 11)
    - "Instructor in English" I & II (Box 11)
    - "A Lean Sheaf", Nov. 1956-Dec. 1960 (Box 11)
    - "Lines to a Proud Maiden" (Box 11)
    - "Longing" (Box 11)
    - "Lotus & Other Verses", 1919 (Box 11)
    - "A Moral Lesson" (Box 11)
    - "Mrs. X Speaking" (Box 11)
    - "Only Necessity... (Box 11)
    - "Poems by G.B. Saul", 1912 (Box 11)
    - "Poems: 1921", 3 notebooks (Box 11)
    - "Poems", Aug. 1922 (Box 11)
    - "Poems", Oct. 1922 (Box 11)
    - "Poems", 1922 (Box 11)
    - "Poems", April 1923 (Box 11)
    - "Poems, August, 1923" (Box 11)
    - "Poems, Spring, 1924" (Box 11)
    - "Poems, 1925-1930" (Box 11)
    - "Poems", Nov. 1947 (Box 11)
    - "Postscript to a Halloween", original and duplicate (Box 11)
    - "Reminiscence" (Box 12)
    - "Sonnets", 1917 (Box 12)
    - "A Sophomore Remarks" (Box 12)
    - "Tears, Idle Tears..." (Box 12)
    - "Thirsts" (Box 12)
    - "Verse by George Brandon Saul", 1921 (Box 12)
    - "The White Maiden", 1919 (Box 12)
    - "Winds and Bells", 1919; 2 copies (Box 12)
    - "Zoological Aversions" (Box 12)
  - Short Stories
    - Retellings of Irish Short Stories (Box 12)
    - "Vagaries" (Box 12)
    - "The Vision" (Box 12)
  - Speeches and Lectures
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Theses
    - "A.E. Coppard: His Life and His Poetry to the Publication of the 'Bibliography' ", 1931; doctoral thesis (copy) (Box 12)
    - "The Poetry of Austin Clark" (Box 12)
  - By others
    - T. Henn (Box 12)
- Published material (1966-1967 accessions)
  - Articles about George Brandon Saul
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
  - Articles by George Brandon Saul
    - "Ancient and Medieval Irish Literature" (Box 12)
    - "The Brief Fiction of Sean O'Faolain" (Box 12)
    - "A Consideration of Frank O'Connor's Short Stories" (Box 12)
    - "Daughter of Vikings: Irah Dineren" (Box 13)
    - "A Delicate Fabric of Bird Song: The Verse of Sara Teasdale" (Box 13)
    - "The Elusive Stallion: Notes on Poetry" (Box 13)
    - "Flinty Bread: The Verse of Abbie Huston Evans" (Box 13)
    - "A Frenzy of Concentration: Yeats' Verse from 'Responsibilities' to 'The King of the Great Clock Tower' " (Box 13)
    - "Icy Song: The Verse of Elinor Wylie" (Box 13)
    - "In Memoriam: Alfred Edward Housman, 1859-1936" (Box 13)
    - "An Introductory Bibliography in Anglo-Irish Literature" (Box 13)
    - "Jeffores on Yeats" (Box 13)
    - "Minor Irish Miscellany" (Box 13)
    - "Note on a Literary Curiosity" (Box 13)
    - "Of Tales Half-Forgotten", 2 copies (Box 13)
    - "On English Metrics And Certain Absurdities" (Box 13)
    - "On Mercury and Reason: The Criticism of James Stephens" (Box 13)
    - "The Short Stories of Elizabeth Bowen" (Box 13)
    - "The Short Stories of George Moore" (Box 13)
    - "The Short Stories of Seumas O'Kelly" (Box 13)
    - "Silver Daughter of the Puritans" (Box 13)
    - "Strange Gods and Far Places: The Short Stories of Lord Dunsany" (Box 14)
    - "Suggestions Toward a Revised Program in College English" (Box 14)
    - "Thread to a Labyrinth" (Box 14)
  - Books
    - The Age of Yeats (Box 14)
    - Bronze Woman (Box 14)
    - The Celtic Cross (Box 14)
    - The Cup of Sand (Box 14)
    - The Elusive Stallion (Box 14)
    - Handbook of English Grammar and Writing Conventions (Box 14)
    - In Luminous Wind (Box 14)
    - Major Types of English Literature (Box 14)
    - October Sheaf (Box 14)
    - Owl's Watch (Box 15)
    - Prolegomena to the Study of Yeats' Plays (Box 15)
    - Prolegomena to the Study of Yeats' Poems (Box 15)
    - Selected Lyrics (Box 15)
    - The Shadow of the Three Queens (Box 15)
    - Unimagined Rose (Box 15)
  - Books by Others
    - Yeats and the Easter Rising, by Edward Malins (Box 15)
  - Book Reviews about George Brandon Saul
    - Miscellaneous (Box 15)
  - Book Reviews by George Brandon Saul
    - Anabasis, by St. John Pierre (Box 16)
    - Bars and Shadows, by Ralph Chaplin (Box 16)
    - The Beast in his Hunger, by Harry Brown (Box 16)
    - A Book, by Dyana Barnes (Box 16)
    - Bow Down in Jericho, by Byron Herbert Reece (Box 16)
    - Burning Bush, by Karle Wilson Baker (Box 16)
    - The Burnished Blade, by Lawrence Schoonover (Box 16)
    - The Chanty of the Stars, by John Heath-Stubbs (Box 16)
    - Craftsmen of the Word: Three Poets of Modern Russia, by Leonid Strukhovsky (Box 16)
    - The Creaking Stair, by Elizabeth Coatsworth (Box 16)
    - The Death of Captain Nemo, by Robert Hillyer (Box 16)
    - Dialogue With an Angel, by Sister Mary Jeremy (Box 16)
    - Dostoevsky, by Andre Gide (Box 16)
    - The Enchanted Flood, by W.H. Auden (Box 16)
    - England Reclaimed and Other Pieces, by Sir Osbert Sitwell (Box 16)
    - English and Scottish Popular Ballads (Box 16)
    - Fact of Crystal, by Abbie Huston Evans (Box 16)
    - Fingerboard, by Marshall Schacht (Box 16)
    - A Fountain in Kent and Other Poems, by John Frederick Nims (Box 16)
    - The Golden Nightinga le, by Donald A. Stauffer (Box 16)
    - Heavy Hangs the Golden Grain, by Seuman MacManus (Box 16)
    - The Historic Mr. Poe, by N. Bryllion Fagin (Box 16)
    - Inishfallen Fare Thee Well, by Sean O'Casey (Box 16)
    - The Irish: A Character Study, by Sean O'Faolain (Box 16)
    - The Irish Genius, ed. by Devin A. Garrity (Box 16)
    - Late I Have Loved Thee, by Ethel Mannin (Box 16)
    - The Lion and the Lady and Other Poems, by Emma Swan (Box 16)
    - Lost Edition, by Lillian Everts (Box 16)
    - Modern Greek Poetry, by Rae Dalven (Box 16)
    - Moon Over Manhattan, by Jennie M. Polen (Box 16)
    - Nationalism in Modern Anglo-Irish Poetry, by Richard J. Loftus (Box 16)
    - Northern Lights, by Roger Vercel (Box 16)
    - Paterson (Book Three), by William Carlos Williams (Box 16)
    - The Permanence of Yeats: Selected Criticisms, James Hall & Martin Steinman (Box 16)
    - Prize Stories of 1949: The O'Henry Award, by Herschel Brickell (Box 16)
    - A Quarto of Modern Literature, ed. by Leonard Brown (Box 16)
    - Red Wine and Yellow Hair, by Kenneth Patchen (Box 16)
    - Redemption, by Francis Stuart (Box 16)
    - Second Contemporary Verse Anthology, ed. by Charley Wharton Stork (Box 16)
    - Selected Poems, by Ezra Pound (Box 16)
    - Selected Poems, by Edwin Arlington Robinson (Box 16)
    - The Signature of All Things, by Kenneth Rexroth (Box 16)
    - Stranger at Coney Island, by Kenneth Fearing (Box 16)
    - A Summer in Italy, Sean O'Faolain (Box 16)
    - The Tears of the Blind Lions, Thomas Merton (Box 16)
    - Two Lovely Pearls and Other Stories, by Liam O'Flaherty (Box 16)
    - The Unknown Sea, by Francois Maurice (Box 16)
    - The Wager and Other Stories, by Daniel Connery (Box 16)
    - The Writer on his Art, ed. by Walter Allen (Box 16)
    - Yeats: The Man and the Masks, by Richard Ellman (Box 16)
    - Yeats: A Collection of Critical Essays, by John Unterecher (Box 16)
  - Letters to Editors
    - Miscellaneous (Box 16)
  - Newspaper clippings
    - About George Brandon Saul (Box 16)
    - About Ray Browne (Box 16)
  - Poems
    - "All Soul's Monday" (Box 16)
    - "Ballade," "Instructor in English" (Box 16)
    - "Chorus" (Box 16)
    - "Daybreak," "Dust Wandering," "Ending," "The Vision of Death" (Box 16)
    - "Deirdre Remembered" (Box 16)
    - "Epitaph," "Footnote to the Epitaphs," "Mrs. X Speaking" (Box 16)
    - "Fatal Encounter" (Box 16)
    - "Fatal Necessity" (Box 17)
    - "Fragment," "September," "Song," "Sonnet For Eileen" (Box 17)
    - "Gaffer to Grandson" (Box 17)
    - "The Ghost," "The Musician Dead" (Box 17)
    - "The Ghosts" (Box 17)
    - "Ione" (Box 17)
    - "I Thought of You at Fall of Night" (Box 17)
    - "Ladder to an Alexandrine" (Box 17)
    - "The Light Remote" (Box 17)
    - "Little and Lonely Under the Evening Star", 2 copies (Box 17)
    - "May Night Counsel" (Box 17)
    - "Mens Disconsolata" (Box 17)
    - "Mid-March Pastoral for Eileen" (Box 17)
    - "Mid-Summer Night's Premonition" (Box 17)
    - "Note," "Reaffirmation" (Box 17)
    - "Now in the Lapse of Yule" (Box 17)
    - "Old Philosophy," "Revisitations," "Skeptics," "Vigil" (Box 17)
    - "Postscript to a Halloween" (Box 17)
    - "Query in Age" (Box 17)
    - "Rejoinder" (Box 17)
    - "The Sea-Girl's Vengeance" (Box 18)
    - "Suicide" (Box 18)
    - "Threescore" (Box 17)
    - "The Watchers" (Box 18)
  - Programs
    - Miscellaneous (Box 18)
  - Publisher's List of Books (Box 18)
  - Short Stories
    - "Inland Storm" (Box 18)
    - "King Noggin" (Box 18)
    - "Lacrimal Rerun: A Story" (Box 18)
    - "The Vermilion-Headed Man" (Box 18)
  - Thesis
    - "A.E. Coppard: His Life and His Poetry to the Publication of the 'Bibliography' ", doctoral thesis (Box 18)
- Correspondence (1968 additions)
  See also Correspondence (1966-1967 accessions) and Correspondence (1969 additions)
  - 1930-1931, 1964-1968 (Box 1)
- Manuscripts and published works (1968 additions)
  See also
  Manuscripts (1966-1967 accessions)
  Published material (1966-1967 accessions)
  Writings (1969 additions)
  - Bibliographies
    - Works of Hazell Hall, ca. 1930 (Box 1)
  - Book reviews
    - of Walter Maiken's Lord of the Mountain, 1967 (Box 1)